Fred J. Cook Papers
Fred J. Cook Papers
1958-1967
Cook, Fred J.
5.0 linear ft.
Papers of the American journalist, author. Correspondence, book manuscripts and galley proofs.
148900
Biographical History
Fred J. Cook (1911-2003) was an American investigative journalist. Born and raised in New Jersey, he graduated from Rutgers University and began his newspaper career in the 1930s at the Asbury Park Courier. He covered the 1937 Hindenburg disaster as editor of the New Jersey Courier. By 1945 was working for the New York World-Telegram and Sun, writing about crime and its political connections, and contributing regularly to national periodicals such as Nation, American Heritage, and the New York Time Magazine. He also wrote numerous books on political topics, including Alger Hiss, the FBI, Barry Goldwater, the Cuban Missile Crisis, organized crime, the Ku Klux Klan, and Watergate.
When Cook's 1964 book Goldwater: Extremist on the Right was published, it -- and Cook -- were attacked by Conservative evangelist and radio broadcaster Billy James Hargis on his radio show on station WGCB, based in Red Lion, Pennsylvania. Cook sued, arguing that under the Fairness Doctrine he was entitled to free air time to respond to the attack. Red Lion Broadcasting, the company that owned WGCB, decided to challenge the constitutionality of the Fairness Doctrine. The case went to the Supreme Court as Red Lion Broadcasting Co. v. Federal Communications Commission in 1969, which resulted in the Court's ruling that the Fairness Doctrine was constitutional.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Fred J. Cook Papers consist of correspondence, subject files, manuscripts, and published material.
Correspondence, both incoming and outgoing, relates primarily to Cook's lawsuit against Billy James Hargis and WGCB.
Subject files contain an audiotape and published material, also related to Hargis.
Manuscripts includes manuscripts of books (see inventory below for specific titles) and a radio broadcast.
Published material includes two articles and foreign editions (German, Spanish, Portuguese, and French) of several of Cook's books.
Arrangement of the Collection
All material is arranged alphabetically.
Related Material
Copies of several of Cook's books are in the general collection and in the Rare Books holdings. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Journalism; Cook, Fred J.; Authors, American.; Journalists -- United States.; Audiotapes.; Correspondence.; Galley proofs.; Manuscripts for publication.; Authors.; Journalists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence re James Hargis affair
  - Denton, Marion Gray, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Federal Communications Commission, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Hargis, Billy James, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Hogan, Frank S., 1964 (Box 1)
  - K, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Stations
    - Acceptance file, 1964-1965 (Box 1)
    - Not carrying program, 1964-1965 (Box 1)
    - Playing tape, 1964-1965 (Box 1)
    - Uncertain if program was carried, 1964-1965 (Box 1)
  - Trouble file, 1964-1965 (Box 1)
  - W, unidentified, 1964-1965 (Box 1)
- Subject files
  - James Hargis affair, 1962; 1964 (Box 1)
  - Tape, 1965 (Box 1)
- Manuscripts
  - Books
    - Barry Goldwater, Extremist of the Right, 1964; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - The Corrupted Land, 1965; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - The FBI Nobody Knows, 1964
      - Preliminary pages and Chapters 1-3, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Chapters 4-12, 5 folders (Box 3)
      - Notes (Box 3)
    - The Medical Establishment, 1966
      - Chapters 1-5, 5 folders (Box 3)
      - Chapters 6-10, 5 folders (Box 4)
      - Notes (Box 4)
      - Sample pages (Box 4)
    - The Secret Rulers, 1966; galley proofs; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - The Unfinished Story of Alger Hiss, 1958; 5 folders (Box 5)
    - The Warfare State, 1962
      - Chapters 1-5, 4 folders (Box 5)
      - Chapters 6-11, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Notes and index (Box 6)
      - Sample pages (Box 6)
    - What Manner of Man, 1959; 6 folders (Box 6)
    - What So Proudly We Hailed, 1967; original typescript with annotations; typescript carbons; notes; 9 folders (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Franklin Delano Roosevelt: Valiant Leader, undated; typescript (Box 6)
    - Radio broadcast on the Hargis affair, undated (Box 6)
- Published material
  - Articles by
    - "Hate clubs of the air" and "Just call the Dr. for a loan", 1964; 1968 (Box 8)
    - New York's clean air men, 1967 (Box 8)
  - Books by
    - Die rechts-radiken machte in den USA und Goldwater, 1965 (Box 8)
    - El FBI desconicido, 1965 (Box 8)
    - Le FBI inconnu, 1966 (Box 8)
    - O FBI por dentro, 1966 (Box 8)
    - Les veutours de la guerre froide, 1964 (Box 8)
    - O estado militavista, 1964 (Box 8)